我们追求权力
We seek power.
我们建立帝国
We build empires.
我们相互联结
We connect.
但有一个人的生死
But one man's life and death
将会改变千万人的命运
Will touch the lives of millions.
将会改变一个帝国的命运
It will transform the destiny of an empire
改变我们所有人的故事
And change the story of all of us.
这颗星球残酷无情 在无数混乱中
Amidst the chaos of an unforgiving planet,
大多数物种将会在劫难逃
Most species will fail.
但是有一个物种 却有条不紊地进化着
But for one, all the pieces will fall into place,
一串钥匙将开启人类通往胜利的道路
And a set of keys will unlock a path for mankind to triumph.
这就是我们的故事 我们所有人的故事
This is our story, the story of all of us.
耶路撒冷 公元33年
Jerusalem, 33 A.D.
犹太省的首府 已受罗马统治
A provincial city under Roman rule.
一百年了
Occupied for 100 years.
一名男子被判处死刑
A man has been sentenced to death.
今天 他将被处决
Today he'll be executed.
但他的死将成就世界一大宗教
But his death will launch a global religion.
如今 世界上三分之一的人视之为神明
Today, a third of mankind worships in his name...
他就是拿撒勒(耶稣的故乡)的耶稣
Jesus of Nazareth.
耶路撒冷地处罗马帝国东部边缘
Jerusalem is on the eastern edge of the Roman Empire.
道路四通八达 贸易便利
A vast network of roads and trade routes.
人类进步的关键之一
One of the keys to mankind's progress:
就是大众传播
Mass communication.
现在 一种思想在中东诞生
Now, an idea born in the middle east
并在罗马帝国蔓延开来
Can spread around the Roman world.
五十万人在耶路撒冷纪念逾越节
Half a million people are in jerusalem for passover,
这是犹太人纪念离开埃及的节日
The Jewish festival celebrating the exodus from Egypt.
在他们中 有耶稣的追随者
Among them, followers of Jesus.
他们相信他是弥赛亚(犹太人的复国救主)
They believe he is the Messiah.
但他的教诲危及了国家的和平
But his teachings threaten the peace.
正因如此 他将被钉死在十字架上
For that, he will be crucified.
这是罗马特殊的刑罚
Rome's special punishment
为了惩处海盗 奴隶以及国家的敌人
For pirates, slaves and enemies of the state.
千万人死于这种刑罚
Thousands of people died this way,
但我们只记住了一个人
but we remember one man,
只记住了他的死亡
we remember one death
把他的死亡当成是独一无二的
as if it was the only one,
因为这一例死亡改变了世界的每一个地方
because this one death changed every part, every portion,
每一个部分 每一个角落
every corner of the Earth.
人群中 有一个旁观者
In the crowd, a bystander.
他叫西蒙 来自北非的殖民地昔兰尼
Simon from Cyrene, a colony in north Africa.
昔兰尼的西蒙只是
Simon of Cyrene was a guy
碰巧在耶路撒冷
who just happened to be in Jerusalem.
碰巧遇到了这次游行
Here was this procession going by him.
一个男人背着十字架
There was a man carrying a cross,
被罗马士兵包围着
surrounded by Roman soldiers.
"嘿 你过来 背着他的十字架!"
"Hey, come over here and carry this guy's cross!"
因此一个在街上的普通人
And so we've got a common guy on the street
卷入了历史上这一关键的时刻
who's now involved in this pivotal moment in history.
被钉在十字架上要三天才会死
It can take three days to die on a cross.
失血 休克
Blood-loss, shock,
脱水 窒息死亡
Dehydration, suffocation.
十字架上的苦刑是如此普遍
Crucifixions are so common,
以至于罗马人几乎没有记录耶稣的死亡
The Romans barely register Jesus' death.
除了耶稣的朋友和家人
This non-event,
几乎没人注意到这件普通的小事
this thing that nobody noticed except his friends and family,
然而这件事却有力量改变
turned out to have the power to transform
整个罗马帝国
the entire Roman Empire
在过去的两千年
and the course of human history
比其他任何事件都更深刻地改变了
more profoundly than any other single event
人类历史的进程
over the past 2,000 years.
耶稣的追随者将会重述他的故事
The followers of Jesus will retell his story
利用罗马帝国的力量传播耶稣的教诲
And use the power of the empire to spread his message.
耶路撒冷1400英里外
1400 miles from Jerusalem,
是帝国的首都 罗马
The imperial capital, Rome.
这是世界上最大的城市
The largest city on earth.
人口为一百万
Population: one million.
罗马的人口密度
It's two and half times more densely populated
是如今曼哈顿人口密度的2.5倍
Than modern Manhattan.
在耶稣被钉死在十字架上十八年以后
But 18 years after the crucifixion,
连续的干旱导致了食物短缺
A series of droughts creates a food shortage.
罗马每年需要二十万吨的粮食
Rome needs 200,000 tons of grain each year,
否则人们就会挨饿
Or its people will starve.
五分之一的人已有福利救济
One in five are already on welfare.
纽约市市长和华盛顿市市长
The Mayor of New York City, the Mayor of Washington DC,
与治理古代世界最重要的城市的罗马皇帝
faces many of the same problems that the Roman emperors did
面临着很多同样的问题
in managing the most important city of the Ancient World.
罗马的统治者 皇帝克劳狄乌斯
Rome's ruler, Emperor Claudius.
身有残疾 并不可靠
Disabled, insecure,
但却是西方世界最有权力的人
And the most powerful man in the western world.
可以这么说 所有皇帝都要取悦民众
All emperors had to please the populace
让他们能够养家糊口
and bring home the bacon, so to speak.
但克劳狄乌斯要比其他统治者更努力
But Claudius had to try harder than other rulers
才能使他的统治合法化
to legitimize his rule.
作为皇帝 克劳狄乌斯被人们视为天神
As emperor, Claudius is regarded as a god,
但为了能继续掌权 他仍旧需要人民的支持
But he still needs the support of his people to stay in power.
他给穷人分发食物
He orders handouts for the poor.
但是粮食储备不足了
But there's not enough bread to go around.
在罗马 骚乱是人们生活的一部分
Riots were a part of life in Rome,
这是人们向他们的统治者
it was a way that the people had
传递信息的一种方法
of getting messages across to their ruler,
统治者若忽视了人民 就会招致杀生之祸
and the ruler ignored that at their peril.
上一任皇帝 卡里古拉 是被暗杀的
The previous emperor, Caligula, was assassinated.
接下来要轮到克劳狄乌斯了
Claudius could be next.
让皇帝赢得民心最好的方法
The best way for an emperor to win over the public:
就是建设
Build.
罗马城八英里外
8 miles from the city,
是罗马帝国最大的工程项目之一
One of the largest engineering projects in the empire:
一个规模宏大的引水渠
An mighty aqueduct.
为了把水输送到城市
To carry water to the city,
罗马工程师开凿出45英里的路 穿越了乡村
Roman engineers carve a route through 45 miles of countryside.
他们在山中通隧道 在山谷间搭桥
They tunneled through mountains, they bridged across valleys,
他们建造了这些宏大的建筑物
they built these vast structures
跨越了巨大的空间
across huge amounts of space
没有炸药
without dynamite,
没有任何现代的工具
without any kind of modern tools,
那些建筑被建造得如此出色
and yet they're so well built
以至于在罗马文明消亡后的1500年
that 1500 years after the end of the civilization,
它们依旧巍峨伫立着
those structures are still standing.
引水渠利用了重力原理
The aqueduct is powered by gravity.
每隔三百英尺就要让水下流一英尺
It needs to drop one foot every 300.
太陡的话 水会泛滥
Too steep, and the water will overflow.
太浅的话 水会干涸
Too shallow, it'll run dry.
这是高度精密的工程
Precision engineering.
罗马建筑的奥秘在于
The secret to Roman construction:
一种全新的革命性的建筑材料
A revolutionary new building material.
易于塑形 坚如磐石
Easy to mould, it sets rock hard.
这就是混凝土
Concrete.
人们谈论青铜时代和铁器时代
People talk about the Bronze Age and the Iron Age,
但从多方面来看 自从有了罗马人的发明
but in many ways, ever since the Romans,
我们进入了混凝土时代
we've been living in the Concrete Age.
罗马混凝土的关键成分是火山灰
The key ingredient of Roman concrete is volcanic ash.
罗马周围有五十座火山
And Rome is surrounded by 50 volcanoes.
如今 世界人口的三分之二住在
Today, two thirds of mankind live in buildings
混凝土造的房子里
Made of concrete.
引水渠的成本相当于
The aqueduct cost the equivalent
八十七亿五千万美元
Of eight and three quarter billion dollars,
是胡佛水坝建设开支的十倍
Ten times more than the Hoover Dam.
可以想象当人们来到罗马时
You have to imagine people coming into Rome
看到这宏伟的工程
getting some of their first impressions
会对这个帝国的中心城市
about this centre of Empire
留下怎样的印象
from this massive engineering project.
这向世界宣告了罗马帝国的实力
It was advertising Rome's power.
为了让后世知道这鸿图华构为谁所建
So everyone knows who built this wondrous monument,
罗马皇帝决定以自己的名字为之命名作:
The emperor names it after himself:
水绿色的克劳迪娅 意为克劳狄乌斯之水
Aqua Claudia, the waters of Claudius.
整个工程耗时十四年
It takes 14 years to build,
由四十万块石砖
400,000 blocks of stone,
以及六百万立方英尺的混凝土筑成
6 million cubic feet of concrete.
这项水利工程每天可以输送
Rome's aqueducts will deliver
两亿五千万加仑水
250 million gallons of water a day,
可供一千三百座喷泉
Enough for 1300 fountains,
九百个浴缸和一百四十四个厕所同时使用
900 baths and 144 public toilets.
罗马是世界上最发达的城市
Rome is the most advanced city in the world.
拥有六层高的居民楼
Apartment blocks six stories high,
每栋楼可供三百八十个居民居住
Each with up to 380 residents.
在地下建造的下水道系统每天可以清理
Under the roads, a sewage system helps sweep away
五十五吨的生活垃圾
55 tons of waste a day.
城中还有警局
There's a police force,
消防队
A fire brigade,
邮局
A postal service.
三十座图书馆 三个剧院和八十座庙宇
30 libraries, 3 theaters and 80 temples.
罗马是世界上第一座大都市
Rome, the world's first mega-city.
今天 超过半数的人生活在城市里
Today, for the first time in history,
这是史无前例的
Over half of us live in cities.
全球有二十一座城市
Across the world there are 21 cities
人口超过一千万
With a population above 10 million,
它们按照两千年前罗马的蓝图逐渐发展起来
Based on the blueprint pioneered by Rome 2,000 years ago.
但罗马不仅仅是一座城市
But Rome is more than a city,
它是一个帝国
It's an empire.
它将自己的文明传遍欧洲甚至整个世界
It'll spread its civilization across Europe and beyond.
而传播的方式则是
And it will do it...
战争
...by conquest.
公元六十一年
61 A.D.
罗马派出一只两栖舰队前往八百英里外的大陆
An amphibious force 800 miles from Rome.
人类通过战争传播自己的文明
Mankind spreads civilization through conquest.
罗马人正在朝着欧洲西北部边线挺进
The Romans are heading for Europe's north-west frontier.
军队由苏埃托尼乌斯·保利努斯将军指挥
In command, General Suetonius Paulinus.
他冷酷无情 决心坚定
Ruthless, determined,
是罗马的执行者
He's Rome's enforcer.
在镇压了北非殖民地的一场起义后
Having crushed an uprising in North Africa,
他被调到英国去镇压那里的起义
His orders are to do the same in Britain.
二十年间
For twenty years,
英国人一直以游击的方式抵抗罗马帝国的侵略
Britons have waged a guerilla war against Roman occupation.
他们是技艺精湛的骑士 无畏的勇士
Expert riders, fierce warriors,
以搜集敌人的头颅为荣
They collect the heads of their enemies.
反抗势力的首要力量 是一群神秘的牧师:
Leading the resistance, a mystical sect of priests:
德鲁伊人(德鲁伊是凯尔特民族的神职人员)
The Druids.
他们敬仰太阳 月亮和丛林
They worship the sun, the moon and the forests.
德鲁伊原意为'橡树人'
Druid means 'man of oak'.
罗马记载者将他们称之为野蛮人
Roman writers regard them as barbarians,
而且还声称他们施行人祭
And claim they practice human sacrifice:
" 圣坛上堆满了恐怖的祭品
"The altars were heaped with hideous offerings,
" 每棵树上都沾满血污 "
"And every tree was sprinkled with human gore."
罗马觊觎英国丰富的自然资源
Rome has its eyes on Britain's natural riches:
那些珍贵的金属资源
Its precious metals.
这片土地的深处储藏着铅
Deep underground, lead,
它是制造水渠的必备原料
vital for aqueducts.
而铁 铜和锡则可用来铸造武器
Iron, copper and tin, for tools and weapons.
至于银 则可用来资助罗马军队
And silver, to bankroll Roman armies.
罗马经济的发展是建立在
Rome's economic model was built
其战略扩张的基础上的
on expanding the empire.
而扩张的前提是拥有
To do that, you need to have
一支经久不衰的 能够不断战斗的
a perpetual war machine that's capable
强大军队
of conquest after conquest.
罗马将近一半的开支都用于军队建设
Up to 50% of Rome's spending goes on the military,
比今天美国政府在军队的开支的两倍还多
More than double the proportion the us government spends today.
这是人类历史上第一支全职专业军队
Mankind's first full-time, professional army.
每个士兵都配有一柄短剑
Each soldier is armed with a gladius,
短剑由钢铁锻造而成
A short sword made from steel,
专为近战设计
Designed for close-quarter combat.
每名士兵还配有短矛 用作重型标枪
A pilum, a heavyweight javelin,
短矛长七英尺 头部装有可致命的金属尖刺
Seven feet long with a lethal metal spike.
另外 每人还有一个护盾 攻防均可
And a shield, used in defense and attack.
当保利努斯的军队与英国人激战正酣之时
As Paulinus' men make contact with the britons,
记载家塔西佗如是描述着战争场面
The writer tacitus describes the scene:
" 德鲁伊人将双手高举上空
"The Druids lifted their hands to the heavens,
" 唤醒神灵放下巨毒诅咒
"Invoking the gods and pouring forth horrible curses.
" 我军见状惊恐不已"
"Our troops were in awe at such a spectacle."
但保利努斯将军是久经沙场二十年的老兵
But Paulinus has been a commander for 20 years.
他坚信自己有实力击溃敌军
He knows he has the firepower to destroy the rebels.
即使你有激情 也有勇气
You can have passion, you can have guts.
但如果你面对的是像罗马军队一样强大的敌人
But if you run up against a military might like Rome,
你拥有的激情便一文不值
that passion wanes quickly,
勇气也将转化为恐惧
those guts fade to fear,
然后你就沦为了阶下囚
and the next thing you know you're a conquered people.
罗马军队的战术
The battle tactics of the Roman army
都经过了反复的演练
were rehearsed and drilled,
通过不断地演练找到缺陷
and rehearsed and drilled to a fault,
这样在混乱的战场上
so that in the chaos and distraction of battle,
每个士兵都能各司其职 知道自己该干什么
everyone did their job, they knew what to do.
保利努斯的军队结束在英国的任务时
By the time Paulinus is finished in Britain,
击杀人数已达八万人之多
His men kill as many as 80,000 people.
反叛者的据点也被捣毁
The rebel stronghold, destroyed.
而德鲁伊人 也不复存在
The druids, annihilated.
当一片土地被征服后 首要任务便是
Once a land is conquered, the first priority:
建造公路网络
A network of roads.
罗马士兵是全能的士兵
The Roman soldier was a versatile soldier.
他不仅是战场上的杀戮机器
He wasn't just a fighting machine.
还是优秀的工程师
He was an engineer,
铺路工人 造桥工人
a road builder, a bridge builder.
这样一来 便可以很快地从罗马军队调用人手
This meant you could have rapid deployment of the Roman army.
罗马人建造的公路 宽二十三英尺(约七米)
The Roman road, 23 feet across,
可容六列军队并肩前进
Wide enough for an army to march six abreast.
罗马的公路连接着各个村庄
Roman roads connect Roman towns,
被征服的人们成为罗马帝国的公民
And conquered people become citizens of the empire.
巴黎 伦敦 巴塞罗那
Paris, London, Barcelona,
都采用了同样的建筑构造
Laid out to the same design.
澡堂 圣殿 广场
Baths, temples, plazas,
以及竞技场
And an arena,
这里是罗马最据盛名的活动
Home to one of Rome's most popular exports:
角斗比赛的发源地
The games.
角斗表演在当时有很强的娱乐性
Gladiatorial games were mass entertainment.
可以看做是远古时代的真人秀
It's the reality TV of the Ancient World.
罗马帝国中共有四百座竞技场
There are 400 arenas across the empire.
最大的可容纳五万名观众
The largest hold 50,000 people.
观众可免费入场
Admission to the games is free.
每个人都可以成为罗马文明的受益者
Everyone can enjoy the benefits of Roman civilization.
大部分角斗士都是奴隶 被迫战斗
Most gladiators are slaves, forced to fight,
但还有一些人是自由自身
But others are free men,
想通过这种方式寻求名誉和荣耀
looking for fame and glory.
角斗士的汗被搜集起来 装在瓶中
Gladiator sweat is collected, bottled and sold
作为催情剂兜售
As an aphrodisiac.
角斗士就像摇滚巨星 他们有自己的追随者
A gladiator was like a rock star, they had fans.
这在他们的涂鸦中便有体现
You can even see in their graffiti,
里面有女人给他们心爱的角斗士的情话
love notes from women to their favorite gladiators.
最高级别的角斗士一场比赛
A top gladiator can earn
可以得到相当于二十万美元的报酬
the equivalent of $200,000 a fight.
但大部分角斗士活不过二十三岁
But most die before they turn 23.
此时的罗马正处于鼎盛时期
Rome is at the height of its power.
整个帝国统治着欧洲
Its empire dominates Europe,
北非和中东
North Africa and the Middle East.
罗马统治着全球五分之一的人口
A fifth of mankind is under Roman rule.
然而罗马人并不知道 在世界另一端
But unknown to the Romans, on the other side of the world,
有一个像罗马一样庞大和强大的帝国
There is another empire just as big and powerful.
公元166年
166 A.D.
罗马商人们来到了离家五千英里外的地方
Roman merchants, their names lost to history,
如今 他们的名字已湮没在历史长河中
5,000 miles from home.
两年来 他们远渡重洋 翻山越岭 勇闯沙漠
For two years they have crossed oceans, mountains and deserts,
一路朝着印度前进
Heading beyond India
这片他们只曾耳闻未曾目睹过的土地
To a land they've heard of only in whispers.
"在那之外 在这世界的外边缘
"Somewhere out there, on the outer fringe of the world,
"在大海的尽头
"Where the sea ends,
"有一个伟大的内陆国家"
"There is a very great inland state."
那就是中国
China.
他们是在中国的首都洛阳落脚的
They're the first Romans to set foot
首批罗马人
In the Chinese capital, Luoyang.
他们进入了另一个世界
They've entered another world.
在中国洛阳
Luoyang, China.
罗马商人来到了离家五千英里外的地方
Roman merchants 5,000 miles from Rome.
开始研究丝绸
They've come in search of silk.
罗马人迷恋上了中国的丝绸
The Romans were obsessed with Chinese silk.
他们愿意翻山越岭远跨重洋
And they would cross oceans and cross lands
前来寻找这些奇异的外国商品
in pursuit of these exotic foreign goods.
那不是他们生活的必需
It's not what they needed,
却是其心之所向
but they were going after what they wanted.
罗马每年约耗费等同于如今的22亿美元
Romans spend the equivalent of $2.2 billion a year
用于从印度和中亚的商人手里
Importing luxuries like silk
进口丝绸等奢侈品
From Niddlemen in India and central Asia.
但他们不知道丝绸的产地或制作工序
But they don't know where silk comes from or how it's made.
他们以为丝绸是长在树上的
They think it grows on trees.
丝绸手工制造是中国的一个国家机密
Silk manufacturing is a state secret in China.
没有哪个纺织者会告诉外国人其制造流程
No Chinese weaver is to share that knowledge with a foreigner.
中国知道丝绸作为出口商品的价值
China knows the value of its silk as an export commodity.
这是中国保守了三千年的秘密
It's a secret China has guarded for 3,000 years.
这些罗马商人在皇帝的宫殿内
The Roman merchants are granted an audience
做了次观众
In the imperial palace.
汉桓帝
Emperor Huan.
十四岁登基
He came to the throne age 14,
把他的家人从宫廷里肃清出去
And purged his family from the court.
是东方世界里最具权势之人
The most powerful man in the eastern world.
贸易有着吸引人的力量
Trade has fascinating effects,
它不仅包括商品间的交换
it involves the exchange of goods,
也包括来自五湖四海的人们之间的联系
but it also involves the contact of people from different places.
人们彼此会面
People are meeting each other,
说着各自的语言
speaking each other's languages,
逐渐适应对方的文化习惯
adapting to each other's cultural practices,
去学习对方的传统
learning about each other's traditions.
随着贸易往来的进行
The world becomes a more interconnected place,
世界各地间的联结更加紧密
when trade is going on.
皇帝热情迎接了这些罗马人
The emperor welcomes the Romans,
但并未让他们知道丝绸的制作方法
But doesn't let on how silk is made.
如今 这已经不是什么秘密了
Today, it is no longer a secret.
丝绸是蚕吐出的一种天然纤维
Silk is a natural fiber spun by silkworms.
蚕宝宝吐出一种细丝结成茧
Their larvae produce a single thread to make cocoons.
产出一磅丝绸需要两千只蚕
It takes 2,000 silkworms to make a pound of silk.
在接下来的三百年里
For the next 300 years,
中国仍旧是世界的丝绸出口大国
China remains the world's great exporter of silk.
丝绸的出口路线一直向西延伸
It travels west,
穿过印度 中东 最后进入欧洲
Through India, the Middle East and into Europe.
形成一条长达五千英里的商路
A 5,000-mile trade route:
这就是丝绸之路
The silk road.
罗马人想要丝绸 而中国人有
The Romans wanted it, the Chinese have it,
因此 东西方世界有史以来
and, as a result, silk connected the east and west
第一次因丝绸而联系在一起
for the very first time in human history.
丝绸之路成为某种渠道
The Silk Road becomes a kind of channel
随之而来的是不同的商品 人民 思想
along which goods, people, ideas,
军队和宗教间的相互往来
armies, religions are moving back and forth.
贸易兴盛繁荣
Trade booms.
而随之也带来了思想的涌动
But also, the flow of ideas.
那些即将改变人类未来的思想方兴未艾
Ideas that'll transform the future of mankind.
在叙利亚首都大马士革
Damascus, Syria.
耶稣被钉死在十字架上的四年之后
Four years after the crucifixion.
有一个人正在逃亡路上
A man is on the run.
他就是保罗
Paul.
一名传道者 一个闹事者
Preacher, troublemaker,
也是基督教历史中最重要的皈依者
And the most important convert in the story of christianity.
在他还未信奉基督教 逃亡大马士革的路上
Before his conversion on the road to Damascus,
他曾迫害过基督徒
He persecuted christians.
但现在 他将让一个无关紧要的教派
But now he will turn an insignificant sect
变成一种世界性的宗教
Into a world religion.
今天 人们尊称他为圣徒保罗
Today, he's known as Saint Paul.
他激情四射
He was a passionate guy,
他勇气过人
he was a guy with grit.
他虔诚地信仰着自己的上帝
He really believed in his God,
真心相信他的福音
really believed in his gospel,
诚心相信基督是唯一的救赎
really believed that Christ was the only way.
为了传播基督就是弥赛亚(救世主)的讯息
For spreading the message that Christ is the Messiah,
保罗被通缉了
Paul is a wanted man.
对犹太统治者来说 他是个异教徒
To Jewish leaders, he's a heretic.
对罗马人来说 他是个煽动者
To the Romans, a rabble-rouser.
如果被捕 他将被处以极刑
If caught, he'll be executed.
大马士革是一座石墙包围的城池
Damascus is a walled city.
每个门都有重兵把守
Every gate is heavily guarded.
保罗的逃亡路线...
Paul's escape route...
便是越墙而过
Over the walls.
接下来的二十年里 保罗游历了罗马帝国
For twenty years, Paul travels the Roman Empire
他和其他的信徒们相互联系
Contacting other believers,
传递着希望之音
Spreading a message of hope.
他告诉人们
He's telling people,
"基督教能让人获得救赎
"Christianity creates a salvation for anyone.
"如果有个奴隶 一直被其主人虐待
"If you have a slave who's being abused by his master,
"此生悲惨万分 那在来世
"Who has a horrible life, in the next life,
"他的主人会得到应有的报应
"His master will get what he deserves
"至于这个奴隶 如果他是个好人
"And the slave, if he's a good man,
"相信基督耶稣并视之为其上帝和救世主
"Who accepts Jesus Christ as his lord and savior
"在来世 他就会得到好报
"Will get what he deserves."
保罗给整个帝国的基督信徒们写了信函
Paul writes letters to fellow Christians around the empire:
有罗马书 帖撒罗尼迦书 格林多书（圣经新约 保罗所著）
Romans, thessalonians and corinthians.
它们几乎占了圣经新约全书中的一半
They make up nearly half of the new testament.
"世间再无犹太人和希腊人之异
"There is no longer Jew or Greek,
"奴隶和自由之身之差 男女之别
"Slave or free, male and female,
"因你们都存在于基督耶稣之下
"For all of you are one in Jesus Christ.
"我们这儿的许多人 在基督里同为一体
"We who are many are one body in Christ.
"爱是恒久忍耐 是温润善良
"Love is patient and kind,
"爱是不嫉妒 自负 傲慢或粗鲁..."
"Love is not jealous or boastful, arrogant or rude..."
这些信件就像我们在阿拉伯之春运动中
Those letters become very much like the Twitter tweets
看到的Twitter网一样
that we see during the Arab Spring.
这就是当时的交流方式
This was the communication of the time
但多数是在罗马的监控之下
and it was very much under the Roman radar.
"我作孩子时 话语像孩子
"When I was a child, I talked like a child,
"思绪像孩子 意念像孩子..."
"I thought like a child, I reasoned as a child..."
保罗将这些信件授与其他信徒
Paul's letters are entrusted to other believers
他们将此传遍罗马帝国
Who deliver them across the empire.
"但当我长大成人 便将孩童之事丢弃"
"But when I became a man, I put away childish things."
在这个时候 罗马已经修建了
By this time, Rome has built
二十五万英里的公路
A quarter of a million miles of roads,
这些路足够绕地球十圈
Enough to circle the earth ten times.
有着连接二百五十个重要港口的航道
Shipping lanes connect 250 major ports.
这就是保罗传播信息的方法
This is how Paul spreads the word.
''信仰 希望与爱三者相伴
"So Faith, Hope and Love abide, these three.
"但最重要的是爱"
"But the greatest of these is Love."
早期基督教的故事证明了
The story of early Christianity really speaks
思想的力量
to the power of ideas,
是思想创造了历史
that is what creates history,
改变了人民
that's what changes people,
造就了文明
that's what makes civilization.
这一切都始于思想
It's ideas, it always starts with ideas.
150年后 在罗马帝国的一个重要港口
150 years later, on the outskirts of Carthage,
迦太基的城郊外
One of the largest ports in the Roman Empire,
常有一群基督教徒们偷偷地会面
A group of Christians meet in secret.
私人民房当做教堂
Private houses double up as churches.
早期的基督教只是
Early Christianity was a religious movement
穷困潦倒之人
for the extremely poor,
奴隶们
for the slaves,
还有女人们参与的宗教运动
and for many women.
基本上 任何在罗马社会没有发言权的人
Basically anyone who didn't have a voice in Roman society
都能在基督教的运动中畅所欲言
could find a voice in the Christian movement.
在罗马法律上 全国有八百万奴隶
Across the empire, 8 million people are slaves
不享有任何权利
With no rights in Roman Law.
三千万妇女无投票权和担任公职的权利
30 million are women who can't vote or hold public office.
在她们当中有个女孩叫佩尔培图阿
Among them, Perpetua.
二十二岁初为人母 颠覆叛逆
22 years old, a new mother, and a subversive.
一年前政府下令
A year earlier, an imperial decree
将基督教定为非法教会
Made conversion to Christianity illegal.
像佩尔培图阿这种皈依者则成为了国家的敌人
Converts like Perpetua are now enemies of the state.
他们的罪行是 拒绝敬拜罗马神灵
Their crime: refusing to honor the Roman Gods.
你得有点疯狂才能成为基督徒
You had to be a little bit crazy to be a Christian,
而这足以让你被处以死刑
it was enough to get you killed,
因为你只忠于
because you were saying your allegiance was
耶稣还有他的父亲
to Christ and to his father
而并未忠于帝国
and not to the emperor.
你会不停地回头看看身后
You would've been always looking over your shoulder,
害怕有人跟踪
like, is someone following me
或者害怕有人知道自己是基督教徒
or does someone know I'm a Christian.
你会偏执多疑 不敢对人敞开心扉
You would've been paranoid, afraid to talk to anyone openly.
帝国的地下警察 也称弗鲁曼塔里
The empire's secret police: the Frumentarii.
他们利用眼线来抓捕异端分子
They use a network of informers to hunt down dissidents.
佩尔培图阿被指控为叛国
Perpetua is charged with treason.
被关进监狱的她等候着残酷命运的到来
She's sent to prison to await her fate.
她喜欢写日记
She keeps a diary,
现存最早的文字
The earliest words that still survive
是由一位基督教妇女写下的:
Written by a Christian woman:
"和我斗争的并不是野兽 而是邪恶
"I am not to fight with beasts but against the devil.
"我知道胜利的曙光已经不远了!"
"And I know that victory is waiting for me!"
信徒们的终极考验...
The ultimate test for any believer...
就是为你的信仰而死
To die for your faith.
基督教徒佩尔培图阿即将面对
Christian dissident Perpetua faces a horrible death
迦太基竞技场上残酷的死刑
In the arena at Carthage.
基督教徒们会被扔向猛兽
Christians are thrown to wild animals,
或全身涂上焦油活埋
Or covered in tar and burned alive,
或者是砍头
Or beheaded.
不过只要佩尔培图阿能够主动信仰罗马教神
But Perpetua can still save herself
她仍然有一线希望活下来
If she makes an offering to the Roman Gods.
罗马人会跟这类人说
The Romans come to these people and they say,
"瞧你给我们惹出的麻烦
"Look you're stirring up trouble for us.
"你公开声明
"Make some public declaration
"说你没有反对这个国家
"That says you're not against the state.
"承认罗马帝国就是你所敬重的神
"Admit that the emperor is a god,
"你就能安然无恙"
"And that'll show that you are okay."
佩尔培图阿的家人前往监狱探望
Perpetua's family visits her in prison.
让她哺育自己的孩子
She's allowed to nurse her baby.
她的父亲乞求她回心转意
Her father pleads with her to back down
接受罗马人的条件
And accept the Roman rules.
他说: "孩子 想想我吧"
"Daughter,' he said, 'have pity on me,
"别丢下我
"do not abandon me,
"想想你的孩子吧 放弃你的自尊吧!"
"have pity on your baby, give up your pride!"
"我尽力安慰他 对他说
"I tried to comfort him, saying,
"事事均会依上帝之愿发生"
"It will happen as God wills."
真正的基督教徒不能抨击自己的宗教
A real Christian can't denounce their religion,
无论是公开场合还是私下
they can't do it in public, they can't do it in private,
即使在心里也不能这样做
they can't do it in their heart,
如果做了就会在地狱中永受煎熬 这就是信仰
because they will burn in hell forever, that's the belief.
可以想象这需要多大的勇气
Imagine how profoundly courageous one had to be,
将生死置之度外 然后骄傲地说
to put your life on the line and say,
"是的 我是一名基督教徒"
"Yes, I am a follower of Jesus the Christ."
这样做需要的勇气 这样简单的行为
The courage to do that, that simple act,
足以说明信仰的力量
speaks volumes about the power of faith.
根据她日记的记载
According to her diary,
佩尔培图阿自愿接受死刑
Perpetua goes willingly to her death.
她的勇气感动了一名监狱看守
Her courage inspires one of the prison guards,
他叫布田 之后他也加入了基督教
A man called Pudens, to convert.
数千名基督教徒被处以死刑
Thousands of Christians are executed.
他们就是人们所尊称的殉道者
They become known as martyrs.
但是罗马人杀死的基督教徒越多
But the more Christians the Romans kill,
基督教就越是盛行
The more popular the religion becomes.
一百年间 基督教徒数量
In 100 years, the number of followers grows
由二十万上升到六百万
from 200,000 to six million.
在罗马 每十人中就有一名基督教徒
1 in 10 people in the empire is Christian.
从北非到英国
From North Africa to Britain,
这个宗教变得如此流行
The religion becomes so common
因此所有禁止它的法律均被废除
all laws against it are lifted.
之后 一个转折点来了
And then, a watershed moment.
公元337年
The year is 337.
君士坦丁大帝驾崩
The emperor Constantine is dying.
临终前他做出了一个决定
He makes a decision that will shape the future
决定了整个罗马帝国的未来
Of the Roman Empire.
"我久久期盼的时刻终于到来
"The time is arrived I have long hoped for,
"作为一个虔诚的祷告者
"With an earnest desire and prayer,
"我可能会得到主的救赎"
"That I might obtain the salvation of God."
西方世界最强大的人接受了洗礼
The most powerful man in the western world is baptized.
数百年来
For hundreds of years,
基督教一直被罗马帝国欺凌
Christianity was being quelled,
镇压甚至是迫害
and put down by the Roman Empire, even persecuted.
不过现在信奉基督教就没事了
Now it's okay to be a Christian.
从君士坦丁大帝接受洗礼以来
Once Constantine is baptized,
整个帝国就改变了对基督教的态度
the whole empire then shifts towards Christianity,
这时候如果有人想从中获得
and then anybody who wants a stake in it,
政治上或者经济上的利益
politically and economically,
就需要成为基督教徒
needs to be a Christian as well.
新的基督教中心在帝国的东方崛起
A new Christian capital rises in the east of the empire:
那就是君士坦丁堡 也就是现在的伊斯坦布尔
Constantinople, today Istanbul.
城中心矗立着一座比罗马任何寺庙都大的教堂
At its heart, a church larger than any temple in Rome.
圣索菲亚大教堂 圣神智慧的殿堂
Hagia Sophia, the church of the holy wisdom.
今天 全球有二十二亿的基督教徒
Today there are 2.2 billion Christians,
占世界总人口的三分之一
Nearly a third of the world's population.
基督的追随者们改变了世界的每一个地方
His followers have changed every part, every portion,
每一个部分 每一个角落
every corner of the earth,
这一切都归功于两千年前的这个人
and that has to be understood as the power of this one person
所带来的力量
over 2,000 years ago.
在中东 一个男人的死亡
One man's death in the Middle East
让一种新的讯息在世界各地广泛传播
Inspires a message that spreads around the world,
世界从未像这般紧密相连
A world connected like never before.
基督教是罗马帝国留下的一笔永恒的遗产
Christianity, the lasting legacy of the Roman Empire.
但在帝国衰落后 我们重建自己的家园
But when empires fall, we remake our world.
我们不断创新 探索...
We innovate and explore...
新的思想和机遇随之而来
New ideas, new opportunities.
但同样 新的冲突也无可避免
But also new conflicts.
这就是文明间的相互碰撞
A clash of civilizations.